{"tossups": [{"question": "Maurice Brodie developed a remedy for this disease while a research assistant at NYU, and John Enders was awarded the 1954 Nobel for his cultivation of this virus in the lab. The first live vaccine for this disease was tested at Letchworth Village in New York City. One sufferer of this disease had a bathtub installed on the<em> USS Iowa</em> for its treatment and founded the March of Dimes. For ten points, name this virus that paralyzed FDR.", "answer": "<b> polio</b>myelitis", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Augustus the Strong was dethroned during this war, and one side in this war attacked in a blinding snowstorm, winning the Battle of Narva. The turning point of this war saw General Adam Lewenhaupt and his Caroleans defeated while attempting to storm the Great Redoubt. That battle forced the exile of the losing ruler, Charles XII. For ten points, name this war, mostly fought between Russia and Sweden, which saw the Battle of Poltava won by Peter the Great.", "answer": "<b> Great Northern War</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This commodity is mined from sulfide ore in the Escondida near Antofagasta. A mine for this metal and gold in Copiap\u00b4o collapsed in 2010, trapping 33 miners for over two months. The Atacama Desert is rich in this metal, making Chile the world\u2019s leader in its production. For ten points, name this conductive metal which alloys with tin to make bronze.", "answer": "<b> copper</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Francis Heney prosecuted this city\u2019s Mayor Eugene Schmitz in a series of 1908 graft trials. William Ralston constructed the Palace Hotel in this city, which was later burned down after a disaster here killed the fire chief, Dennis Sullivan. The neighborhoods of North Beach and Telegraph Hill in this city were heavily damaged in that disaster, which featured heavy underreporting of casualties in this city\u2019s Chinatown district. For ten points, name this California city which suffered a devastating earthquake in 1906.", "answer": "<b> San Francisco</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This ruler, who described himself as the \u201cBeloved of the Gods,\u201d protected his power by assassinating his half-brother Susima. This patron of the Great Stupa at Sanchi and son of Bindusara ruled from Magadha. His visions of bloodshed after winning the Kalinga War led him to convert to Buddhism. For ten points, name this grandson of Chandragupta and emperor of the Mauryans.", "answer": "<b> Ashok</b>a the Great", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Suzanne Massie taught this politician to \u201ctrust, but verify.\u201d As governor, he signed the Therapeutic Abortion Act and banned public carry of firearms with the Mulford Act. As President, he launched an invasion to protect American medical students, Operation Urgent Fury, which deposed Maurice Bishop in Grenada. For ten points, name this U.S. President who served as Governor of California after his acting career.", "answer": "Ronald<b> Reagan</b> <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man accused Mitch McConnell of telling an \u201cout-right lie\u201d with regards to the Export-Import Bank. He criticized the Obama administration\u2019s handling of the death of Darren Goforth, a sheriff\u2019s deputy in this man\u2019s state. This successor to Kay Bailey Hutchinson filibustered the Affordable Care Act in 2013 shortly after being elected as the junior Senator from Texas. For ten points, name this Republican senator and 2016 Presidential candidate.", "answer": "Ted<b> Cruz</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s retirement was delayed by a scandal concerning Louis Wolfson. The John Birch Society put up posters urging the impeachment of this man, and his court ruled school prayer unconstitutional in <em>Engel v. Vitale</em>. This Supreme Court justice\u2019s court presided over cases which greatly expanded the rights of criminals, such as<em> Gideon v. Wainwright</em>. For ten points, name this liberal Chief Justice, a former Governor of California, who served from 1953 to 1969.", "answer": "Earl<b> Warren</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One of the first cities of this civilization was said to have held the Abzu temple to a water god. The world\u2019s oldest surviving law code, found at Nippur, came from this civilization\u2019s king \u2014 Ur-Nammu. An ancient text from this civilization lists its kings, but omits the Lagash dynasty. The First Dynasty of \u2014Uruk includes a man whose friend Enkidu dies after helping him; that man was the legendary Gilgamesh. For ten points, name this Mesopotamian civilization that was conquered by Sargon the Great.", "answer": "<b> Sumer</b>ia", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Solomon Southwick was this party\u2019s unsuccessful nominee for Governor of New York in 1828, and it grew in popularity after William Morgan\u2019s alleged killing by a group on the Niagara River. This earliest 3rd party in the U.S. nominated William Wirt for President in the 1832 election. For ten points, name this single-issue party that eventually merged with the Whig Party and opposed a certain secret society.", "answer": "<b> Anti-Masonic</b> Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Albert of Mainz\u2019s desire for cathedrals prompted the writing of this document, which was anticipated by a similar document written by Andreas Karlstadt. It ends by casting away prophets who say \u201cPeace, peace!\u201d without providing peace. The papal bull<em> Exsurge Domine</em> [ex-oor-gay doh-me-nay] identified 41 mistakes in this work. For ten points, name this list of complaints directed towards the Catholic Church and its policy of indulgences that was apocryphally nailed to a door in Wittenberg by Martin Luther.", "answer": "<b> 95 Theses</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Sherron Watkins blew the whistle on this company, which caused blackouts in California in 2000 with its manipulative speculating. The Sarbanes-Oxley Act was passed in the wake of</b> <b>this company\u2019s end, after which the (+)</b> <b>Arthur Andersen accounting firm was discredited</b> <b>and Jeff Skilling and (*)</b> Ken Lay were convicted of fraud. For ten points, name this energy company based in Houston, Texas, which suffered the largest Chapter 11 bankruptcy in U.S. history in 2001.", "answer": "<b> Enron</b> Corporation", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s ministry saw the passage of the Railways act, which was introduced by this man\u2019s minister of transport, Eric Geddes. This man won the \u201cCoupon election\u201d against Andrew Bonar (+) Law, and avoided war with Turkey after an invasion of the Dardanelles in the Chanak Crisis. While Minister of the Exchequer under Herbert Asquith, this man championed the (*) </b> People\u2019s Budget, and this man\u2019s ministry saw women gain the right to vote in Great Britain. For ten points, name this Welsh British prime minister of the Liberal party who led Great Britain at the Versailles Conference.", "answer": "David<b> Lloyd George</b> (prompt on partial last name)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A former employee of this organization alleged that \u201ccompany men A and F\u201d wanted to fix a 2002 event in favor of Los Angeles. Bill Kennedy, another employee of this organization,</b> <b>came out as (+)</b> <b>gay in December 2015 after being the target of a homophobic slur by</b> <b>Rajon Rondo. Former referee (*)</b> Tim Donaghy gambled on games run by this organization under commissioner David Stern. For ten points, name this professional sports league that may have rigged the 1984 draft lottery to give Patrick Ewing to the New York Knicks.", "answer": "<b> National Basketball Association</b> (or<b> NBA</b>; accept<b> National Basketball Referees Association</b> or<b> NBRA</b> or descriptions thereof)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>One of this man\u2019s operas includes a scene in which an elderly Edgar Ray Killen recounts his role in a trio of 1964 Mississippi murders, and primarily depicts the final battle and</b> <b>surrender of the Confederate Army. This composer of (+)</b> <em><b>Appomattox</b></em><b> dramatized the</b> <b>reign of a monotheistic pharaoh in the final part of his \u201cPortrait Trilogy\u201d and inserted five scene-change \u201cknee plays\u201d in a five-hour opera about the title (*) </b> physicist. For ten points, what American minimalist wrote the operas<em> Akhnaten</em> and<em> Einstein on the Beach</em>?", "answer": "Philip<b> Glass</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "<b>One philosophical split in this movement pitted Lysander Spooner\u2019s arguments against those of Wendell Phillips\u2019 \u201cdisunionists.\u201d Bates College and Oberlin College were founded</b> <b>in support of this movement, and (+)</b> <b>Elijah Lovejoy was killed by a mob in Illinois for</b> <b>supporting it. Newspapers devoted to this cause included (*)</b><em> The North Star</em> and<em> The Liberator</em>, published by William Lloyd Garrison. For ten points, name this movement led by Frederick Douglass, whose goal was to end slavery.", "answer": "<b> abolition</b>ism (or<b> abolition</b> of slavery; accept<b> end</b>ing<b> slavery</b> or equivalents before \u201cslavery\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Sociologist George Ritzer used this company as a metaphor for cultural homogenization. Thomas Friedman has claimed that no two countries where this company does business have ever gone to war with each other. Since 1986, the price of this corporation\u2019s signature</b> <b>product has been used in an (+)</b> <b>\u201cindex\u201d measuring purchasing power by</b><em><b> The Economist</b></em><b>.</b> <b>\u201cindex\u201d measuring purchasing power by</b><em><b> The Economist</b></em><b>.</b> <b>Stella Liebeck\u2019s lawsuit against this corporation was explored in the documentary (*)</b> <b>Stella Liebeck\u2019s lawsuit against this corporation was explored in the documentary (*)</b> <em>Hot</em> <em>Coffee</em>. For ten points, name this fast food restaurant chain that sells the Big Mac.", "answer": "<b> McDonald\u2019s</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "<b>Former President Rutherford B. Hayes arbitrated a land dispute in the aftermath of this war, in which the losing general was killed during the battle of Cerro Cor\u00b4a. It began after</b> <b>the invasion of Mato Grosso, leading (+)</b> <b>Dom Pedro II, Bartolome Mitre, and Venancio</b> <b>Dom Pedro II, Bartolome Mitre, and Venancio</b> <b>Dom Pedro II, Bartolome Mitre, and Venancio</b> <b>Flores to form a coalition against Francisco Solano Lopez.</b> <b>Flores to form a coalition against Francisco Solano Lopez.</b> <b>Over half of (*)</b> Paraguay\u2019s population was killed in, for ten points, what war against an alliance of Argentina, Uruguay, and Brazil?", "answer": "War of the<b> Triple Alliance</b> (accept<b> Paraguayan</b> War before Paraguay is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Representatives of this city declared \u201cthe weak suffer what they must\u201d before destroying the town of Melos. This city won the Battle of Sphacteria, but it was later subjected to the</b> <b>rule of the (+)</b> <b>Thirty Tyrants after losing the Battle of Aegospotami.</b> <b>Thirty Tyrants after losing the Battle of Aegospotami.</b> <b>This city, which</b> <b>was connected to its port at (*)</b> <b>was connected to its port at (*)</b> Piraeus by the Long Walls, lost its maritime empire after it led a Piraeus by the Long Walls, lost its maritime empire after it led a disastrous offensive against Syracuse. For ten points, name this city that launched the Sicilian Expedition during the Second Peloponnesian War against Sparta.", "answer": "<b> Athens</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker! (1) <b>The</b><em><b> Athenaeum</b></em><b> magazine published many works in this language in the 19th</b> <b>century, and the poet Novalis wrote his works in this language before dying at age</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The \u201cBlood and Soil\u201d movement in this language\u2019s literature included such (+)</b> <b>anti-Semitic novels as</b><em><b> The Toadstool</b></em><b>, which accused Jews of molesting children.</b> <b>The authors in the (*) </b> Weimar Classicism movement wrote in this language, including the playwright Friedrich Schiller. For ten points, name this native tongue of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe [ger-tuh], which he used to write<em> Faust</em>.", "answer": "<b> German</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}], "bonuses": []}